the comment section of last week's video
I saw a comment like this
Here's how I responded
Today I'm here to fulfill my promise
Hello everyone
I am A K, focusing on using UGC Anime to popularize AI.
In this video, I will share my personal 4-month self-learning experience
Let me share in detail how I started learning AI from scratch.
Let's start by talking about methods in the first half
In the latter part, we'll discuss the mindset.
To learn AI well, the first step must be to put down your phone
sit back in front of the computer
I don't mean to make you stop Showbiz
focus on learning
but the phone is merely an information retrieval tool
The computer is the real productivity tool.
Don't argue with 'you can also code and deploy large models on a phone'
No need for that
Now, sit back in front of your computer
Please learn to use a computer first
Here, 'using' does not refer to browsing the web
but understanding what a disk partition is
What is file hierarchy
What is a file path
and what different file types are used for
How to quickly locate the root directory of a software or file
How to invoke the command line
What are the differences between command lines invoked in different paths, etc.
Then the know-it-all will surely start typing away on the keyboard
If you don't even understand such basic knowledge, you'd better not learn AI.
What I want to say is
Don't forget you also started as a beginner
Stop it, Ah Dong, watch your words.
After mastering basic computer operations
You also need to grasp the basic principles of AI.
At the very least, you need to understand what those frequently mentioned terms and tools are actually used for.
I've covered this in detail in my previous two videos
Friends who haven't watched it are recommended to go back and take a look
Of course, what I said is actually quite simple
But there's really a lot to learn
In the past, I would have thought there was indeed a threshold.
But now with various chatbot products available
The acquisition of Knowledge is really not too easy
I highly recommend everyone develop the habit of using Doubao
I recommend it because its overall capabilities are truly top-tier in the country.
Of course, if you have the capability, I would recommend Gemini even more.
I recommend GEMINI more
Newcomers don't need to force themselves
It's actually sufficient to make good use of domestic tools first
Alright, once you've grasped the theory, it's time to start practicing.
How my AI workstation was built
It has been discussed in great detail in the previous video.
Here I want to delve a bit deeper
that is how to develop tools and build confidence
Developing tools is actually quite simple
Communicate with the Agent using natural language
The agent I use is Claude Code
Newbies shouldn't chase after any Skills at the beginning
what MCP tool
First, align with your own needs
develop a small tool that can help yourself
For example, let's start by building an AI news aggregation tool
No need to make it too complicated
Just set up 3 to 5 news sources.
Which news sources are better
You can first ask Deepseek or Doubao
After asking, go into the Agent and tell it
I want to create an automated news gathering tool
then clearly articulate the specific requirements
If you don't know how to articulate the specific requirements
go back to Deepseek
Ask him I want to make a news search tool
but I don't know how to describe my needs
help me
Just treat it like a mentor or a partner to chat with
As you chat, the requirements become clearer
Then go back to the Agent and let it do the work
As you keep working on it, something decent starts to take shape.
Then it's all about continuous improvement and optimization.
face difficulties and solve them
For example, I created a news scraping tool for myself.
and a tool for automatically extracting video transcripts
Simply put, when you personally create something that works,
the exhilarating feeling brought by efficiency improvement
more effective than watching tutorials 10,000 times
This is the real motivation to keep going
The third step sounds simple
but it also tests human nature the most
That is persistence in improvement
For example, I make it a daily routine to spend a fixed amount of time browsing GitHub and watching videos from top-tier creators.
and high-quality blogger videos
Then I would find ways to integrate those scattered tools together
continuously pushing the limits of new technologies
but it does no harm and only good
Because I know I'm not just learning tools
it is also training my ability to integrate information
hands-on practice ability
and the topic selection ability for self-media
Additionally, I have one more output component than the average person.
that is, making videos
But this thing can't be mastered quickly.
I don't recommend pushing yourself this hard at the beginning
but if you can share your insights and achievements with others after learning
share your insights and achievements with those around you
It will definitely be a huge help for learning.
Don't doubt me
This is what the extremely famous Feynman learning technique says
Huh? No!
Aren't these three steps just about starting with theory, then practice, and finally persistence?
Is there really no shortcut?
Actually, there is.
but it's probably not the kind most people want to hear
If you don't believe me, let me talk to you about
the most fundamental trick to learning
that is, the mental approach
Let me start with a bold statement
Mindset is a hundred million times more important than methods
100 million copies
If this logic doesn't click
even if you're given 10,000 methods
in the end, it still can't be executed
And the core of the mindset is, you have to ask yourself honestly
What is the purpose of learning AI?
If your answer is 'learning AI is to make money'
then there's no need to read the following content
because making money should be the outcome, not the goal
What you need to do is identify the needs
then learn AI to meet the needs
The second point of the mindset is to understand
The only person you can truly rely on in this world is yourself.
You must develop the ability to solve problems independently
This used to be a hurdle
Now there are various AI chatbot tools
is really no longer a problem at all
I spent these 4 months completely immersed in Gemini, practically inseparable from it.
It's now even closer to me than my wife is to me.
The third point of the mindset approach
it is crucial to recognize the drawbacks brought by grand narratives
like those contents talking about energy and the future of humanity
Just take it as entertainment, don't take it too seriously
What difference does it make if we ordinary people know that energy is important?
Could you possibly work on nuclear fusion?
Watching too much of this kind of content will only make your 'eyes grow higher'
only makes your eyes grow higher
"hands getting lower"
Acknowledging your ordinariness is the beginning of becoming extraordinary.
Stay humble and focus on your current growth
is the first step to becoming stronger
The fourth point of the mental approach
is to always believe that you are the most important product
All learning and improvement must be centered around building yourself up.
If you're skilled, using tools can make you even more powerful.
If you're weak, tools in your hands are just a pile of scrap metal
Don't expect tools to completely transform you.
I know and believe that there will be a day when AI replaces all of humanity
But if you just lie flat now
I'm afraid I won't even catch a glimpse of the Great Harmony world
OK, that's all for this video
I'm AK, dedicated to popularizing AI through UGC Anime, smooth sailing and it's already six o'clock!
Off work!~